hey I'll check out the audio book of Lu
Rockwell's fascism versus capitalism
narrated by me
Scott Horton at audible.com it's a great
collection of his essays and speeches on
the important tradition of Liberty from
medieval history to the Ron Paul
revolution rock will blast our status
enemies profiles our greatest
libertarian heroes and prescribes the
path forward in the battle against
Leviathan fascism versus capitalism by
Lew Rockwell for audiobook find it at
audible Amazon iTunes or just click in
the right margin of my website at Scott
Horton org all right you guys welcome
back I'm Scott Horton it's my show the
Scott Horton show live here on the
Liberty radio network noon to 2:00
Eastern Time 11:00 to 1:00 Texas time
next up it's another former CIA
counterterrorism officer this time it's
John Kiriakou associate fellow at the
Institute for Policy Studies a former
CIA officer and former senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee won't wear that part
welcome to show how are you hey thanks
for having me I appreciate you joining
us today so this is the first time we've
spoken and I think it's probably pretty
likely we will again considering the
kind of things you like writing about
nowadays but so first of all I was
wondering if we could do a little bit of
just to get to know you think that
perhaps starting with the first time
that you were as far as I know on TV
claiming I believe you later said that
you were misinformed and it wasn't a
deliberate lie that only three people
have been waterboarded and what's the
big deal and and I don't know the story
that well John but my understanding is
something along the lines you found out
that that really wasn't true and then he
decided to become an anti torture
activist something along those lines I
tried to make two points in an interview
that I did with ABC News in December of
2007 and the two points were that I'm
sorry three points were that the CIA was
torturing its prisoners that torture was
official US government policy and not
the result of some rogue operatives and
three that the policy had been approved
by the president
now the mistake that I made was in
saying that that the issue of torture
could be could be looked at in two ways
number one was it moral and was it right
and I said it was not it was immoral but
the second was did it work
and I said that I believed it had work
because the reporting from the field
from these secret prisons where torture
was taking place indicated that it was
working at least that's what we were
being told inside the CIA now we know
now from the CIA inspector general's
report that was released in 2009 and
especially from the Senate torture
report that that was a lie that the
reporting from the field was that the
torture was not working but once that
reporting got back to headquarters CIA
leaders were telling CIA employees that
it was working and that we were going to
continue with this program but then so
you were already retired at that point
or they put you on TV to say because
when I remember that and and maybe this
was just because this is what stuck out
to me the most but it seems to me
thinking back on it that the headline
that came out of it was only three guys
were waterboarded and it was Khalid
Sheikh Mohammed you'd waterboard him
yourself who cares about him and that
was what we all learned from the
previous interview that interview that
got this all started well a lot of the
right-wing media picked it up and and
parsed it and chose to report only what
they wanted to hear
that was my first that was my first
lesson in dealing with the press that
the press is generally healing through
its own agenda and that the press is
ideological one way or the other and
there are very few members of the press
who were really interested in the truth
so you're right what came out of that
interview was not what I said but what a
lot of right-wing media wanted to hear
and that's what they repeated and that's
what I got out of it was what I didn't
want to hear and and and I admit John
that actually I think even after you
decided that you were gonna you know
talk about torture in a much more
forthright way
to that I still held it against you that
yeah that's the guy that said that only
three or water or whatever and it turned
out they put you in prison for the truth
that you told about this torture program
so can we now go back to before that
terrible interview and who and what you
were at the CIA what you knew about or
what any role you had in the torture
program or any of that stuff and make
all that clear and then explain you know
where he went after that interview and
Baltimore prison yeah
I joined the CIA in January of 1990 as
an analyst focused on mostly on Iraq and
I did that for about seven and a half
years I got bored and I switched to
operations that was a very unusual
switch but but I spoke both Greek and
Arabic and I wanted to go overseas so I
moved to the Directorate of operations
in 1997 and spent the next seven and a
half years working in counterterrorism
so after September 11th I was I was
named the chief of the CIA's
counter-terrorist operations in Pakistan
and in that role I led a series of raids
in March of 2002 that resulted in the
capture of 52 al Qaeda figures including
Abu Zubaydah who at the time we believed
was the number three in al-qaeda that
turned out to not be true in fact Abu
Zubaydah was never a member of al Qaeda
he certainly helped al Qaeda
he ran their training camps he served as
sort of a logistician but he never
pledged fealty or loyalty to some of bin
Laden that was just bad information that
we have so I went back to headquarters
in 2002 I remained until March of 2004
and I resigned to to take a job in the
private sector and then in 2007 in in
December of 2007 I got a call from Brian
Ross at ABC News who said that he had a
source who said that I had tortured Abu
Zubaydah I said that was absolutely
untrue I was the only person who was
kind to others Abeyta I said I've never
laid a hand on him or anybody else in
fact
when I got back from Pakistan I was
approached by a senior officer in the
CIA's Counterterrorism Center who asked
if I wanted to go through training that
would certify me in what he called
enhanced interrogation techniques I said
I didn't know what that meant
enhanced interrogation techniques and he
said we're gonna start getting rough
with these people and he explained to me
what these torture techniques were I
said look I have a visceral problem with
this I don't want to be I don't want to
be involved and I I had nothing to do
with it
but then in 2007 Brian Ross made this
call and I denied that I had anything
whatsoever to do with the torture
program and he said well you're welcome
to come on the show and defend yourself
so that same week within just a day or
two of that phone call President Bush
went on TV and in response to a
reporter's question said he looked right
in the camera and he said we do not
torture and then later in the week
see I knew that was a lie but later in
the week he said that if there was
torture it was the result of a rogue CIA
officer and I thought my god they're
gonna try to pin this on me
somebody told Brian Ross that I was the
one doing this so I decided okay I'm
gonna go on ABC and I'm gonna defend
myself now I went on ABC and I defended
myself with with incorrect information
all I knew was what I had been told by
colleagues or former colleagues former
co-workers in the CIA's Counterterrorism
Center that the torture did work that
was a lie that was a lie perpetrated by
senior CIA officers not just to other
CIA officers but to Congress into the
White House as well all right and then
so after that how did you get in so much
trouble that they locked you in the pen
because it's predict ulis when people
say that in the entire torture program
the only guy that was ever held
accountable was a guy who had told the
truth about it rather than participated
in right
the very next day after that interview
the CIA filed what's called a crimes
report against me with the FBI and the
FBI began investigating me that
investigation lasted from 2000 from
December of 2007 until January of 2012
they ended up charging me with five
felonies I will admit to you that that I
made one mistake I confirmed the name of
a former CIA colleague who was involved
in the torture program to a reporter who
wanted to interview him
the reporter never contacted him and
never released the name but I was
charged with a felony count of violating
the intelligence identities Protection
Act and then for the interview I was
charged with three counts of espionage
and then just for good measure they
threw in a felony counts of making a
false statement as well all right now
hold it right there we'll be right back
everybody with John Kiriakou forgot to
say he's got an article at anti-war calm
today let's talk about torture and we're
gonna do some more that on the other
side of this
hey y'all Scott here for samurai tech
Academy at master samurai tech calm
modern appliance repair requires true
technicians who control will shoot their
high tech electronics if you're young
and looking to make some real money or
you've been at it a while and just need
to keep your skills up to date
samurai tech Academy teaches at all and
they'll also show you the business how
to own and run your own take a free
sample course to see how easily you can
learn appliance repair from master
samurai tech comm use coupon code Scott
wording for 10% off any course or set of
courses at master samurai tech comm all
right shell welcome back talking with
John Kiriakou former CIA officer author
of this new article let's talk about
torture running at anti-war calm today
and we got it from other words they said
we could now where we left off you went
to prison for espionage for talking to
an American reporter which I think no
matter who we're talking to on you know
about pretty much anything people got to
understand you know just how crazy that
is right there that federal charges can
be applied
in ways where the meaning of words has
to be completely destroyed and then but
they can do it anyway I mean it might as
well charge you for weapons of mass
destruction for having an unregistered
handgun because hey as long as we're
making up stuff I mean what is espionage
about talking to an American reporter
that must have been what your lawyer
told the court right it was it would
have been funny if it had been so
serious and you know the lead espionage
charge I should add all three of the
espionage charges were dropped
as was the whole famous charge but the
the lead espionage charge said that I
had revealed top secret code word
information to a reporter from the New
York Times and the information had been
Declassified solely for the purpose of
prosecuting me and that information was
that after the 9/11 attacks the CIA had
a program to kill or capture members of
al Qaeda oh yeah yeah I allegedly said
that in 2008 so apparently that was so
top secret protected that I needed to be
charged with espionage which which in
its extreme form is it is a death
penalty charge and then I got two other
charges of espionage as well now the
other two espionage charges were even
funnier I had worked with a with an
analyst who left the CIA to work for
Mitchell and Jessen the two notorious
creators of the torture program the two
psychologists and this former colleague
had given me his business card so a
reporter from the New York Times said
hey do you know how I can get in touch
with this guy and I said you know I
haven't talked to him in years but I
have his business card and I gave him a
copy of the business card and then I
gave another copy to a reporter for ABC
and I was charged with two counts of
espionage for for giving them that
business card now this is a CIA officer
who had never been undercover in his
life and his business card specifically
says Mitchell and Jessen associates
which everybody in America
new had created the torture program but
somehow that that business card was so
highly classified that it warranted to
additional espionage charges for me and
then what wasn't you were eventually
convicted of only I was convicted of
violating the intelligence identities
Protection Act of 1982 I was only the
second American ever charged with with
violating that law and what I did was uh
I was working for ABC News at the time
and one of my colleagues there said hey
do you know how I can get in touch with
somebody from the rendition detention
and interrogation program I said I
really didn't know any of those guys and
he said well you mentioned a guy in your
book who you saw on the tarmac in
Pakistan at an airport when we were
transporting a mr. bata and he says I'm
gonna call him John he says you know you
called him John and I said oh right
that's John Doe I don't know whatever
happened to him he's probably retired by
now that conversation put me in prison
for two years because that officer was
undercover and I confirmed his last name
now the reporter never contacted this
guy and the name was never released to
the public but but it bought me a felony
conviction forfeiture of my pension and
two years in prison well now so that
wasn't the real reason that they
launching up know what was ya know I
maintained and my attorneys maintained
from the very beginning that the CIA was
so angry that I had that I had outed
them on the waterboarding issue and that
I continued to talk about torture that
that they just asked the the Justice
Department to find something find
anything with which they could charge me
you know I want to add to there's an
awesome book that came out in 2012
written by Harvey silverglade who's a
professor of law at Harvard University
and it's called three felonies a day and
he argues in this book that we are so
over criminalized in this country that
the average person on the average day
going about his normal business commits
three felonies every day and so if
you're
subject of a federal investigation and
they really want to get you they're
gonna get you whether it's with the
conspiracy laws mail fraud wire fraud I
mean those those laws are so broadly
written the thinking they can apply to
just about anybody on almost any day and
that's really what they did in my case
well and in fact a few years ago they
officially legalized just within just
Department guidelines going out on
fishing expeditions tour and targeting
people not crimes its official policy
now that's just not how they really
operate that's how they operate you know
one of the things that really struck me
as as hypocritical and funny in a you
know not in a haha way but in an odd way
is one of the things they did with me
was they said your honor he was seeking
to build a business and he was seeking
to capitalize on this monetarily well
first of all that was utter nonsense
they knew what my bank accounts looked
like because they had access to them and
I was broke and I mean I was literally
broke after I went on ABC I lost my job
I lost my contract I lost everything in
fact it was the prosecutor who went on
to a six million dollar a year job at a
big-name firm in Chicago
it's the prosecutors who end up running
for governor we're running for president
it's not the the the people who you know
allegedly committed these crimes there
was no money involved right all right
now so I'm glad we got a chance to talk
about that but now we have little time
to really get into that but I want to
say a couple things from the news here
just to bring this car into why this is
still important Jeb Bush will not rule
out resuming the use of torture is the
headline at the hill newspaper yesterday
and at the intercept there's a piece
where they point out an interview with
CIA executive director cron guard where
he says quote well let's put it this way
it you know meaning the stress positions
that are are meant to make him as
uncomfortable as possible so I assume
for without getting into semantics
that's torture I'm comfortable with
saying that we were told by legal
authorities that we could torture people
and quote now correct me if I'm wrong
but he's going a little bit off script
here the struct is what we did if
somebody else did it might have been
tortured but when we do it it's an
enhanced interrogation technique that
does not rise to level a torture because
if it did they might have to go to
prison for that Scott you are exactly
right this is the issue and this is what
we need to be shouting from the rooftops
it's all about the semantics you've got
you've got George Tenet now Porter Goss
and Mike Hayden three former directors
of the CIA and eight former I'm sorry
and five former deputy directors coming
out with a book soon saying exactly the
same thing if we do it it's not torture
if the Justice Department says it's
legal it's not torture that's semantics
and the reason why they're so up in arms
about this is because this is their
legacy when their obituaries are written
they're going to say that these men were
instrumental in implementing the torture
program and they don't want to go down
in history as tortures they want to go
down in history as Patriot now I don't
doubt their patriotism however misplaced
it might be but we need to call this
what it is it's torture and we need to
accept responsibility for it now if if
they're of the ideological persuasion
that torture is something that they
needed to do okay that's fine I suppose
we can all agree to disagree on an issue
like that but we can't continue to play
games that that then finally indicates
that it wasn't torture and that it
worked because it was torture and it
didn't work and those are historic facts
yeah well a couple things there I mean
first of all though I'm not certain
that's true I think it didn't work if
you assume the premise that the goal was
to gain good intelligence to protect the
American people but that's fairy tale
you know Disney World crap the purpose
was to hurt this guy until he says he's
friends with
hüseyin and it weren't perfect for that
didn't it that's right yes you know in
the halls at the CIA while Dick Cheney
was was leaking information to the press
false information in the press
linking saddam hussein to al-qaeda in
the halls of the CIA we called that the
big lie
and I remember analysts like myself who
had spent you know most of our adult
adult lives working on Iraq
I remember thinking surely no educated
American is going to place any
intellectual value on this at all
al-qaeda hated Saddam Hussein more than
they hated us there was nothing Muslim
about Saddam Hussein at all he famously
made a trip to Mecca to make the ohm
rather minor pilgrimage and didn't even
know the prayers and had to have an aide
whisper the prayers into his ear so
there there was nothing religious or
Muslim about him at all and there was
certainly no tie whatsoever between
Saddam Hussein and al-qaeda none in fact
in the two or three weeks before the
invasion
Osama put out a podcast urging the
people of Iraq to rise up and overthrow
the socialist infidel Saddam and fight
the Americans - that's right
that's exactly right it was all a big
lie and it all came out of Dick Cheney's
office all right now so then the other
point is something that is almost
unbelievable to me and I'm sorry I'm
keeping you an extra minute here if
that's okay George Tenet Porter Goss
Michael Hayden and several of their
underlings I presume that means they're
lawyers they're writing a book together
to justify torture they don't have all
the power in that sentence they don't
have a PR adviser who could tell them to
just shut the eff up about it right now
I said the same thing yesterday to a
former colleague why can't they just let
it go and like I said the only
conclusion that I can come to is that
this is their legacy this is this is how
history is going to remember them and
they think somehow in their warped
little minds that they're going to be
able to twist the truth and to twist
history and to convince people you know
who you know have to be either stupid or
or so gullible that they just
know any better that this this terrible
program work especially when I mean the
what's the introductory chapter here is
you can trust me tenet and him Hayden
because we were in charge of the CIA and
NSA on September 11th so we really know
what we're talking about that's the
other part of their legacy they're the
greatest failure in the history of all
bureaucrats in all of humanity it really
was it was the greatest intelligence
failure in the history of the country
and somehow none of them have borne any
responsibility for it well by the way
now that we're going to that and you
were there in some capacity I want to
ask you about the rich bleed podcast
especially Part two you may be familiar
where Richard Clarke when confronted
with just how much George Tenet
absolutely knew must have known about
the San Diego group is just
flabbergasted and says well man I don't
know I guess they must have been trying
to recruit them and and I can't believe
that he lied to me about this for so
long because according to Clarke he
intended would talk on the phone like
girlfriends late into the night about
al-qaeda all the time and and George
Tenet was keeping from him the director
of counterterrorism in the White House
that there was real ass al-qaida in the
country how do you account for that I
know both Dick Clark and George Tenet
personally and I can tell you that if
Dick Clark says that George Tenet was
lying to him then George Tenet was lying
to him and that's just how George
operated he was an intensely secretive
person even at the cost of a September
11 style attack Dick Clark was one of
the most highly respected
non-ideological
counterterrorism professionals in
government anywhere in government and I
mean even on Capitol Hill and nobody
wanted to disrupt an attack like
September 11th as much as dick Clarke
did talk about shouting from the
rooftops it was Dick Clark who had gone
to condi rice and said you're not
listening to me there's going to be a
terrible attack and it's going to be
so for George Tenet to lie it really
goes to the core of who George Tenet is
and again if Dick Clark says Tennant's a
liar tenets a liar yeah well you know
Michael Sawyer your former colleague has
told the story on the show and in print
too to James Bamford and and it's been
told other places where the CIA were
tented at the time was Director of
Central Intelligence boss of all the
different agencies and CIA kept trying
to get NSA to share their intercepts
from the Yemen switchboard house and
they wouldn't and supposedly at least
CIA had to build their own intercept
station on Madagascar but they could
only get half the conversation and tenet
would never make Haydon share the
intercepts with the bin Laden unit is
that really how business is done up
there come on because a lot of this
sounds like yeah you know I don't know
cover for something or another it was
even worse in the CIA's dealings with
the FBI
at least at least we had you know mutual
respect between CIA and NSA colleague to
colleague but our relations with the
with the FBI were actively hostile and
I've always been convinced that that
that's why the September 11th hijackers
were able to move around the country
like they did because we hated the FBI
and they hated the CIA and so no
information was exchanged but Mike sure
is exactly right you know make sure
there's another one who who was sort of
you know shouting into the wilderness he
was warning people as best he could that
something terrible was going to happen
and nobody would listen to him and here
the whole time
the operations people probably were on
these 9/11 hijackers at least the ones
in San Diego and you know those of us
who were supposed to be working against
al-qaeda didn't even have any idea of it
yeah well not so have you read the 28
pages no I wish I had but here's another
thing you know it's Bob Graham not only
was he one of the most highly respected
members of the Senate he was one of the
most highly respected members of the
Senate Intelligence Committee and if Bob
Graham says that those 28 pages would
shake our government to its foundation
uh I believe Bob Graham and if you know
if leaks and room
about Saudi involvement or what's in
those 28 pages I'm gonna believe that
the Saudi government was involved yeah
well listen I I would rather err on the
side of conspiracy kukri rather than
letting a CIA guy spin me if I have to
if it comes down to it so what about
what could be pretty reasonably inferred
here possibly if you were to assume that
Dick Cheney's mean enough to say I don't
know torture people to death
maybe he would work with Bandar Bush to
make sure that al Qaeda had enough guys
to get on those planes to carry out
their successful attack because they had
some agendas and they liked Pearl Harbor
attacks what about that I told Paul Jay
at the real news network when he posed
almost exactly the same question I said
in my heart I don't want to allow myself
to believe that something like that
could possibly happen but with that said
there there seems to be a lot of
circumstantial evidence to indicate that
it may have happened at least some
version of what you just said
may have happened and we know that we
know that the Bush family and the
messiah's family go back generations we
know that we know that nobody was closer
than george w bush and prince Bandar I
mean you know weekends at each other's
homes and Camp David and vacations
together so you know I've gotten myself
to the point where I'll believe just
about just about anything and until
until the White House decides to
declassify these 28 pages I just don't
know what else people are supposed to
conclude well I guess we could just bomb
Iran all right hey thanks very much for
coming on the show John good to talk to
you thanks for having me good to talk to
you all right so that is John Kiriakou
he's writing here for other words that's
other words org and we're reprinting
this one today at anti-war calm it's
called let's talk about torture and he
is limb page down here at the Institute
for Policy Studies
hey I'll guess what you can now order
transfer
of any interview I've done for the
incredibly reasonable price of two and a
half bucks each listen finding a good
transcriptionist is near impossible but
I've got one now just go to Scott
Wharton org slash transcripts enter the
name and date of the interview you want
written up click the PayPal button and
I'll have it in your email in 72 hours
max you don't need a PayPal account to
do this man I'm really gonna have to
learn how to talk more good that's Cal
Wharton org slash transcripts you hate
government one of them libertarian types
maybe you just can't stand the president
gun grabbers and war mongers me too
that's why I invented Liberty stickers
calm well Rick owns and now and I didn't
make up all of them but still if you're
driving around and want to tell everyone
else how wrong their politics are
there's only one place to go Liberty
stickers calm has got your bumper
covered left right libertarian Empire
police state founders quote central
banking yes bumper stickers about
central banking lots of them and well
everything that matters liberty stickers
calm everyone else's stickers suck hey
I'll Scott were here to tell you about
this great new book by Michael Swanson
the war state and the war state Swanson
examines how presidents Truman
Eisenhower and Kennedy both expanded and
fought to limit the rise of the new
national security state after World War
two
this nation is ever to live up to its
creed of liberty and prosperity for
everyone we are going to have to abolish
the Empire know your enemy get the war
state by Michael Swanson it's available
at your local bookstore or at amazon.com
and Kindle or in paperback just click
the book in the right margin as Skywarn
org or the war State calm
you